OK。
啊！
再去決定唔行動嘅。
punish or whatever it is on those offending universities.
not taking the appropriate action, and what are the criteria for for that?
Cause of events that you not going to.
As I said, I will try. Let me begin by saying I didn't. I hope I didn't say I was happy.
How to answer, but at least explain to us how this has happened, and who actually decides on
Dr. Albert, this is the third time you you have to answer such question. I think if you can further explain your path to happiness and why you need to lay the path that you have that restriction, I think what we basically from
PAC point of view, we look into financial, but there are other aspect that financial analysis cannot be justified just as a pure factor to to your flexibility. Can you explain to the honourable Chen?
我哋而家可以繼續繼續啊！開會啊，Tanya，你頭先問嗰個係咪銀就係二點二點二五嗰個份係嘛？啊，主席係啊，因為其實你知道誒，關於嗰個誒二點三零嚇，即係或者成個落去，因為成個段落都係關於呢一個有冇追。
遵從收生嗰個規則嘅，咁呢一個咧，亦都同辯覽咧，即係嗰個程序辯覽當中咧，三點一二咧就有講到咧收生不足嘅時候咧，誒包括咧列出咧少收咗嘅學生，即係話頭先嗰四誒百分之四嗰個誒可以接受程度啦，同埋咧如果遇到特殊嘅情況咧就。
就可以酌情處理。咁當然亦都記得咧，頭先咧，阿阿安禮時博士咧都有提及過咧，就係就住咧好多誒不遵從嘅，特別係一啲誒修生不足嘅情況之下咧，就有咧誒聽取佢哋嘅解釋同埋表示happy啊。如果根據佢講法係，即係佢話係。
happy係啦，happy with嗰啲explanations嘅。噉我都想問下主席咧，即係借問咧，因為頭先即係表十二嗰度咧，大家都見得到咧。當然咧，好大部分都係涉及咧係超收嘅。咁但係咧，包括誒誒，如果包含呢一個誒收生不足佢嗰啲，我想了解下嗰啲explanation有。
幾happy，即係誒，我哋可唔可以瞭解下嗰個情況？因為收生不足咧，而冇採取行動咧，我哋覺得相當相當緊要嘅。好啊，即係嗱誒，第一，我想問一問誒阿阿博士咧，就係誒係邊啲人去決定唔採取行動，或者至少去審核佢哋嘅解釋誒，而又再。
嗯。
因為。
所以，他們得要管理入學通過錄取。
rather than punish with withdrawing funds.
Sometimes every four years, or at the
I would rather personally, I would rather attempt to modify behaviour.
If I'm satisfied, then I will take no financial action.
In a programme, it's only at the front end. Universities cannot adjust enrolment by failing students. That'd be terrible.
But and as I explained earlier, enrolment planning is extremely difficult in the light of new school examinations, where offers are made.
Who takes the decision? Well, in my case, in this last few years that I've been Secretary General, my colleagues and I, but I had the responsibility. I can't speak for my predecessor, but I'm pretty sure it'd be the same.
我理解大學的問題。我喺大學工作咗35年，我理解招生規劃的困難。大學校長有難度管理數百個課程。
Each of which might overenrol by one or underenrol by one. Now that single case, that single student, is not important. But when aggregated up across a whole university, it leads to perhaps four per cent or the like.
Based on predicted grades, they're met or they're not met, and sometimes students disappear. And by the time the semesters started, it's difficult to manage that process easily, especially at university level.
And they do that for undergraduate students, still knowing as a 15,000 cap. So an under-enrolment cannot easily be easily be managed with a single year's over-enrolment because we break the 15,000 rule. So we have to be very careful.
I may have said I was satisfied with the explanation. There's a whole world of difference. I'm never happy with under-enrolment, but if I hear a coherent explanation, and the university puts in place steps to rebalance the enrolment, now remember admission happens once.
I will try. Thank you. No problem. But if you can't try, if you can't convince us, you can write a paper so that that will help us to to appreciate your position. Education is not something that is a number crunching. I think from that angle you can explain. I'm sorry, I'm not teaching you how.
Have I helped?
個因素咧出唔到嚟。
所以，the the management of enrolment inside the university has to be a partnership between the the management, the council and the UGC.
tighten this up. It was it was a good recommendation from the director of audit. We will certainly follow up. I don't want to make promises because I I need to consult the council.
嗯，多謝主席。頭先阿Richard提到咧，就係一年之前咧，同學就開始要登記嘅，所以咧呢個咧有時間上面嘅分別第一點。
經過咗一個時間，你改善去點收多咗生喺度，或者你畀多啲資料我哋，噉我哋就可以瞭解多啲嚇。即係用翻教育學院嘅情況，又是教師大學，即係教育學教育大學嚇，即係誒喺一方面嚟咁去解解畀我哋聽嚇。
By persuasion and talking to the talking to the council chairs and the president, and let me just explain somebody else who's very important in this hierarchy is the councils. The councils are each of them the supreme governing body of the university. They hear regular reports from the president much more often than I do, or UGC does.
我亦都同意，要 come back with some some explanation of two of the cases on table twelve， which we're happy to do。局長，你可唔可以去解釋下？譬如講，你用翻教育學院嘅情況，去啲而家過去好似用啊，頭先啊陳議文嗰啲問題咧，過去佢收唔夠生，又係現在係。
第二點咧，佢呢個課程本身咧，即係第要決定咧，係咪真係迎合到某一個需要，所以定呢個課程。當呢個課程出咗之後咧，佢哋發現咧喺個報名之後，真正即係呢個嗰個新學期開始嘅時候咧，出現嘅時候咧，發覺有個別嘅同學咧有困難，困難嘅地方咧就係咧個學校因為種種。
個變咗咧，佢佢佢唔嚟咧，都唔係因為我唔中意啊，我轉啊，我改變咗噉樣。個個個困難就喺呢度，所以因為噉嘅實際嘅困難嘅時候咧，變咗咧誒，佢哋都誒教資會啊，其他都會同其他一啲誒學校啊都傾傾話，喂，你放放人啦噉樣樣，即係睇個情況。咁嗱，呢個就係主席好簡單講一個背景嗰度先，就並唔係話佢。
個質素啊，其他啲嘢。第二咧，學校嗰時咧都諗到就話：如果噉嘅情況點樣處理咧？噉樣就特別咧諗翻咧，就咧譬如最近好重視NCS啦，同埋SEN，可唔可以嗰方面咧做多啲功夫？即係佢哋都嘗試用自己唔同嘅方法咧去處理呢一部分。噉我哋好希望咧，即係呢個一治兩治之後咧，誒，我哋唔希望咧。
一路來都係噉嘅，所以咧就咧頭先我一提咗咧，每一每一個三年度嘅呢一個係啊，呢個教資會裏邊嗰個人力策劃嗰度咧，我哋都會睇嘅。如果真係咧，即係即係一路都係經常都係噉嘅時候咧，我哋都會轉。其實咧，今次呢個例子就反映到出嚟。大家記得咧，舊年年底、今年年初嗰陣咧，我講到咧就呢個係啊呢個大學。
呢個踩啲人分地嗰度啦，我我主要用喺我講英文嗰度，即係個三聯嗰度咧，我哋調節咗啲人數嘅，嗰度減咗啲嘅。即係話畀你聽，你噉樣做翻就我真係要減。嗱，就唔係因為即係唔係淨係懲罰性嘅問題，而係咧就點樣啲資源要好正正正當正確噉樣運用噉嘅背景裏邊去做嘅。咁所以咧就咧。
ok.
噉就住。
less serious than underenrolment provided.
provided there's no dilution.
啊，局長，你等阿阿Richard啊，係啊，麻煩聽阿Richard打畀你。
I'm the secretary, sir. Okay.
Thank you for that. Several points. Certainly about improving the notes and procedures, we're happy to review and take take a look at that, to see how we manage over enrolment. But I go back to something I said earlier.
Overenrolment, normally is on a marginal cost basis. If you add one student to a class of 25 to make 26, there's no marginal cost, very little marginal cost.
我唔係一個執行，喺
響嘅，噉我所以咧就想問一問啦，即係就住呢一個超額收薪，或者係即係簡單啲講冇遵從誒所謂嘅即係嗰個規定嘅話，係會唔會有一個誒定立埋個罰則咧？或者起碼即係你點樣去處理佢哋咧？Doctor Richard。
特別誒，主席多謝你畀個機會咧，我解釋一下呢一部分好噉啊。另外咧，亦都誒見到咧，關於呢個收生不足咧誒，如果報告嗰度都有提及咧，就係話誒係咪即係變唔係好清楚？因為點解咁講咧？就係話究竟呢一個誒收生嗰個規則咧，係適用於整個嘅人。
嚟規範啦，誒即係誒人力規劃範疇啊，定係係人力規範範疇之中嘅個別課程噉，我就想問下誒，就住呢一點咧，會唔會喺嚟緊咧？即係譬如話你哋檢視啦，因為我見到咧，我哋枱面咧都誒，即係我哋都有一份咧係二零一六年嘅嘅情。
程序變攬啦，噉我見到咧有部分都係修訂咗嘅，但係啱啱望到咧，即係即係好可惜咧，就二零誒即係三點一二咧，啱啱正正關於誒收生不足嗰度咧，都係仍然冇就呢一點咧有任何嘅修訂。我想問下誒，會唔會就呢個部分會作誒一啲修改咧，或者清就起碼即係清楚翻咧，局長？
係啊，多謝主席。我嘅理解咧就係阿Richard可以再答一答啦。我嘅理解咧就係多謝議員嘅建議。其實佢哋都預計會咁做嘅，都會修訂得到嘅。好，Richard，you like to expand on this? Yes, um, we will certainly review the the adequacy of that provision in the N O P and and look at how we can.
係噉，就住呢個收生不足咧，我哋都見到咧，即係誒有條例，即係有相關嘅誒條例喺度啦。但係咧誒，因為咧誒，正如呢一個文件嗰度咧，即係尤其是表十二嗰度咧，都列出咗咧好多都係超額嘅。咁好多同事都係關注咧，其實超額並非咧，即係可能唔會增。
係一定唔會增撥資源，但係未必唔對現時讀緊嘅同學係令到佢哋平均能夠可能即係個別攞到嘅資源可能有影響。即係譬如話，可能好簡單啫，一個我哋叫tutorial，可能本來十二人變咗十五人、十六人，咁相對上咧，先生能夠對佢嘅照顧都可能有所影響。
啊！
啊！老。
Dr. Richard。
most certainly。
rolling is something we we do as a matter of
and although we don't.
fact as a matter of policy, but that's triennial planning rather than.
We don't just manage universities by sanctions on over-enrolment. For example, in the triennial planning exercise, a serial under-enrolment or over-enrolment would have consequences.
Okay, thank you. Well, first of all, perhaps I didn't express it very carefully. We are happy to review putting a rule for non-compliance with over-enrolment in the NOPS. Happy to consider a review.
所以，如果邊個價值，由邊個評估，如果
Of the unit of resource per student, and for that to happen, it would have to be a semi-variable cost. For example, the example you gave, like increasing a class size from ten to twenty, that would affect the individual student. But I'm assured that the universities would never allow that to happen. They would.
manage it one way or another， and I trust them and their councils。啊啊，主席啊，唔encourage即係唔鼓勵咧，其實最直接就梗係有有規則去規管啦。既然收生不足都可以有百分之四，咁點解即係超收係唔可以有規管咧？而還點都更有彈性啦，係嘛？佢都會按個別情況睇一。
去解釋咁點解唔一次過定明，即係喺檢視嘅時候定明咧？即係嗱，我知道秘書長咧就係即係即係做嘢嘅啫。咁到最後咧都係要即係嚇council去去負責去即係U.G.C嘅council仲要去過啦。但係如果我哋連秘書長聽落都好似唔係好有興趣，即係去加呢一個規則嘅話，
咁其實你好明顯啊，主席啊，點解我咁講咧？你見到表十二啦，年年都有啲嘅，即係等等有幾間我哋冇辦法。之後其實啊，主席我都想問下咧，我哋有冇辦法咧係攞到誒即係細緻啲每一格究竟涉及啲乜嘢學校同埋邊一個項目噉樣啊？即係如果嗱，當呢啲即係。
唔知係咪可以唔公開定？我哋都可以瞭解多少少咧。因為其實我我係最擔心咧，就係你又冇罰則，你直情係冇連守則都冇啊！我唔好話罰唔罰啦。咁但係呢一樣嘢就係正正話你想唔鼓勵就最好㗎，有罰則。噉我就想問下，其實如果既然你都唔鼓勵，點解連考慮擺一個？
條款喺你嘅辯誒，即係辯覽嗰度都都冇呢個噉樣嘅傾向咧。唔該，主席。即係即係誒，陳議員，即係個問題話招邊間大學個意義就唔喺呢一度，就最緊要睇佢個系統有咩問題出現咗。而家個系統即係成個制度咧，就係個制度係有就係有有。
有法不跟咁誒誒，影響到個影響係幾大咧？咁有法不跟就直情係修生不足嗰度，直情有法不跟啦。咁而家超越咗喺依個貼表十二嗰度超越咗，噉你個問題咧就問有冇對其他啲學生個影響？又或者超收嘅時候，佢會唔會可以下？
考慮下，即係你可能係加一個彈性畀佢一個幅度，即係譬如話有好似呢度咁四誒百分之四或者百分之五，但係即係會唔會都係有相關嘅罰則？即係因為你係而家係冇遵從你本來應承咗嘅嘢啊嘛，係要有後果，即係你要令到啲大學雖然佢有彈性，但係同一個時候都要有後果㗎嘛。
私資培訓機構去傾一傾，究竟係用一個乜嘢嘅人力規範嗰個？
咁誒喺呢度，我都容許我花少少時間解釋下，即係教師呢個專業範疇係相對於其他人力，即係誒誒誒。
啊，Candice，你可唔可以誒過一過嚟嚇？誒十分鐘啊，局長我我要出出去同啊主席開開會嚇啊。OK。
個程序嗰部分，好，副秘書長唔該你，多謝主席，亦都多謝陳議員嗰個問題。就誒教育局同教資會秘書處嗰個跟進功夫，我哋其實係一路有做嘅。咁誒就有兩個個案啦，其中就一個個案就係關於誒。
In terms of the the planned student numbers for the next triennium, what is difficult to do is manage on a year to year basis. But by planning enrolment over a triennium and rebalancing the the student numbers and funds to a university who's who's offended in over or under enrolment.
a sanction， but I'm more than happy to look at。好，好，啊，主席，我諗我都可能我表達得唔好咧，即係唔係唔係好清楚嚟。嗰個係罰唔罰則呢個可能係佢有冇連續性噉樣犯噉樣，我覺得呢一句可能要考慮。咁但係如果誒連呢一個界限都冇可能，即係嗰個意向就未必咁清晰啦。咁另外咧就係。
係誒就住我都想問翻教育局㗎。咁其實咧，我哋喺文件嗰度都見到咧，誒好多時候咧，關於一啲尤其是收生不足啊等等啊，或者係就住收非本地生嘅一啲政策嘅改變咧，其實教育局咧都有有指示或者有同意咧，就係教資會都係要去改變佢嘅變。
誒嗰個變冷㗎，咁但係咧就啲變冷即係講啊講咗，你又叫咗佢做啦，但係佢到今日都未做，即係兩年之後都未做嘅。噉我想問下，其實教育局喺當中係點樣跟進，同埋你點樣可以確保得到咧？即係你講嘅嘢，佢哋係會跟咯。局長係係，多謝多謝。Jennifer，多謝局長。
誒，陳淑中議員，你請你繼續嚇係啦。誒，包括誒喺二點三零段啦，就住呢一個係人力範疇課程就收生不足啦，同埋咧係因應非本地生嗰個取錄政策改變咧。誒，第二點三三段咧都有講到咧，教育局咧其實都有要求教資會咧就修訂相應嘅變濫嘅噉，所以我就想誒。
瞭解一下咧，即係當中究竟係教資會當你傻㗎，唔理你啊，定係佢其實你哋都有跟進、有解釋，點解佢哋唔修辯覽？定係諗住即係今次係一次過，係咪而家就係二零一六嘅誒誒一次過再修訂咧？等等，唔該。啊，局長，係多謝多謝主席。啊，我想請副秘書長詳細解釋下嗰。
文件第誒審計報告第二點三零段，關於教師培訓嗰方面嘅咁嗰個咧，其實我哋有同教資會，亦都知道教資會有同誒誒培訓先生嘅院校係有一個商討，就瞭解究竟點解佢哋係唔能夠跟從嗰個人力規劃嗰個指標。
Thank you. Thanks, chairman.
舉手啊，好嘛？有冇啊？
我哋睇翻誒段落。
同事，有關於第二部分嘅問題啊！
有一個最終嗰個嗰個傾談㗎啦，咁或者呢度我都請阿Doctor阿文可以講一講最新嘅情況。好，Doctor阿文唔該你，thank you。
好，咁即係我我我做代主席都應該問一問同事嘅誒意見先嘅。噉啊，我哋最後第三部分咧，我我想即係又係一個好誒宏觀嘅一個啊問題啦。
誒規劃嗰個範疇係有少少唔同嘅。其他譬如以醫生、護士或者其他一啲，譬如職業治療啊、放射治療嗰啲咧，係一個劃一嘅一個標準。但喺教師呢一個專業裏邊咧，其實嗰個收生嗰個課程其實有好多個唔同嘅類別嘅。有啲係誒全日制嘅學士學位，有啲係已經係在職嘅教師嘅培。
培訓，亦都有啲可能係幼師嘅培訓，即係變咗佢哋有好多唔同嘅所謂嗰個所謂個program嚇。咁每一個呢啲噉樣嘅範疇咧，佢都有一個誒誒收生嗰個限額。咁但係呢一個安排對於一個師資培訓機構係乜嘢最好嘅安排咧？咁教資會而家其實就係同緊師資培訓機構去睇一睇，究竟呢樣。
嘢係咪一個最好安排？整體嗰個數字其實就係冇乜點超收，或者係誒誒誒係收生係不足嘅。整體係其實係足夠，但係就係個別嗰個所謂唔同嘅範疇裏邊，可能係嗰個收生個情況係有差異啦。咁喺呢一方面，我哋都要求咗教資處同誒教誒教資會同埋誒。
限額係一個比較合適啲嘅安排，一個硬指標定係一個所謂一個誒，我哋叫range咧，即係有一個範，即係即係一個範圍範圍幅度畀佢哋做一個收生嘅編配，係比較合合適啲咧。就呢一方面，佢哋研究緊，所以我哋係跟進緊嘅。咁第二方面就係關於嗰個誒文件第二點三二至二點三四段，關於嗰個。
非本地學生嗰個，sorry，我哋叫四in十六out，而家變咗做二十out，二十out呢一個誒誒誒誒誒改變，咁呢個就係因應翻，其實喺立法會誒教事務委員會都有一個好詳細嘅討論，即係都希望我哋就話喺收非本地生嗰陣咧，唔好影響到本地嗰個學額，所以就有。
一個噉樣嘅改變，就呢方面，我哋亦都同教資處誒誒教資會係跟進，希望佢哋睇下用一個乜嘢方法去落實呢個政策上面嘅轉變。而其中一個落實方法就係以改變呢個誒程序變藍，係希希望係用呢一個方法係可以達得到。但係咧，正如頭先啊Dr. Richard Armour都有提及過，就係話喺
收生嗰個安排上邊咧，係需要同個別院校去傾一傾，係用一個咩方法？對於佢哋有冇製造一個困難咧？噉樣樣，咁呢方面佢哋同院校係跟進咗，然後就再喺呢個程序變諗嗰個修改度，希望可以做到一個方法係誒唔會造成一個係一個誒實行唔到嘅安排嚇。所以我哋係希望係。
我落實到嘅安排，我明白。咁但係即係我哋梗係唔想令到佢哋太過綁手綁腳啦。但係同一即係亦都要反映佢哋嘅需求。但係有冇話時間表？因為其實件事都已經過咗差唔多兩整年㗎啦。噉就唔知會唔會有目標噉樣咧？係副秘書長，唔該。多謝主席，多謝陳議員。就呢個，我咁誒，我哋同教召會已經差唔多去。
I think I need to draw the distinction between the bureau asking us to revise a policy and amending the NOPS. If I recall correctly, my colleagues will correct me if I'm wrong. We implemented the policy by writing to the universities straight away. Meanwhile, we've been reviewing the mechanism and whether the NOPS is the right vehicle.
and that latter part has been the subject of discussion with with a number of of institutions, but we did follow the bureau's advice straight away. We wrote to the universities and say we are going to change this policy. This is what it's going to say, and we'll talk to you about how exactly it's going to be implemented.嗯嗯好啊，主席，我有一個好誒基。
基本嘅問題，我想問，其實咧有冇個有冇三年呢一個計劃？有冇原因？即係關唔關咧？大部分嘅大學學學課咧，即係誒嗰個課程咧，以前係三年制嘅，但係而家改咗四年。其實呢個三年定咗落嚟咧，其實同嗰個大學嘅主要嗰個課程係有冇關嘅？即係個年。
數有冇關嘅？係邊位答啊？阿副秘書長或者Doctor Armah？副秘書長唔該。好多謝主席，多謝陳議員問題。或者我首先簡單答答完後，我諗阿Doctor Richard Armah可以再詳細解釋。誒，同學制上面係咪有一個必然直接嘅關係咧？其實就未必嘅，因為咧，其實香港個學制變化其實都有唔同嘅。我諗大家都記的記憶猶新。
就話喺八十年代咁都有三年制同埋四年制嘅大學啦，咁跟住後嚟轉咗做三年制，而家喺誒新高中學制完成咗之後，又轉翻做四年制嚇。咁所以嗰個誒我哋所謂嘅training funding cycle就冇同一個學制嗰個變化係直接掛鈎，亦都因為咧，譬如喺唔同嘅。
嗯，阿審計處長。
噉啊，就誒。
邊位可以答一答呢個問題咧？表十六。
課程嘅研究生即係誒research-based嘅postgraduate students啦。
足嘅計算啦，嗱，究竟呢個計算方法，我或者誒請？
該年度申請誒縮位嘅同學嘅數目減翻縮位嚟計出嚟嘅咧，呢一個所謂不足。
誒資料畀到我哋咧，多謝主席。或者呢方面，我或者請阿Dr. Richard Armour可以提一提供關於嗰個，Dr. Armour，基本上嗰個，嗯。
三點六嗰度噉啊！段落三點六嗰度咧，就係誒寫出咗誒學生宿位同埋教學空間，即係兩樣都唔夠啦。咁而家講講講個學生宿位嘅問題先啦。
誒局方又好，或者審計處長都好咧，可唔可以解釋下呢個計算方法究竟係以誒三點六B羅馬數字一二三加埋，然後減翻你嗰個誒縮位啊？亦或係以？
或者你同事，誒，或者我請我同事，或者誒，其實秘書秘書長或者秘書處會瞭解呢個計算嘅方法嘅個細節係點樣清楚啲嘅啊？啊，副秘書長，你有冇啲？
About top post graduates. Well, first of all, it's up to universities how they deploy their hostel spaces. But in the calculation, in the entitlement calculation, we don't allow for top post graduates because they're self-financing. That's the simple reason.
The the shortfall is against an entitlement. Entitlement. The entitlement is calculated using formula that you've seen the the previous pages. Once that's calculated up, then each university has a has a hostel space entitlement. We measure the actual spaces against the entitlement. You find a shortfall.
本科，譬如建築、法律、醫生、醫生好多好多學科，亦都唔係一定係三年制。三年制主要誒三年嗰個funding cycle嗰個主要嘅目的，最主要就係提供一個延續性同埋肯定性，畀啲大學作為一個所謂規劃嗰個用途。好好OK。Any additional comments from you? Very very little. Just just to
I mentioned as well that three is not a magic number, nor is four. Sure, the normative undergraduate curriculum is four years, but there are many other academic activities in universities which are one, two, three, five, six years. So there's nothing special about any particular year. We think three is reasonable. Our universities are content.
The government is content, and there's no need to change it. It's a long enough planning frame to manage enrolment and also to manage funding. So the university see no, and UGC sees no need to change. 好，陳議員。冇。仲有冇問題？冇。係。誒，仲有冇？
嗱，如果冇嘅時候咧，我哋誒進入啊第三部分，即係第三部分咧就係關於administration of capital grants。嗯，未問過問題嘅同事就呢個非經常補助金嘅管理誒，有冇同事想提問題啊？而家？
三點六B嗰度咧就話啊，以下修讀教資會資助課課程嘅學生就應該嗱，應該啊should誒獲得提供嘅學生縮位嘅有三類型學生咧係要係誒應該獲得提供縮位，第一咧就係非本地學生，第二咧就係研究。
第三咧就係每天交通時間超過四小時嘅學士學位啊課程學生咁咁即係嗱第一呢呢三三三類型嘅誒同學先啦，咁但係我第一樣已經睇到咧，如果咧誒有個人咧係讀呢個誒port嘅master degree嘅，要係local student又超過四個鐘頭咧。
咧噉就冇㗎啦個縮位，咁呢個啊少少奇怪咧。呢呢呢一個嘅誒三類型嘅同學，咁即係呢呢個我我我我遲啲先問，因為呢個都係涉及政策嘅問題。但係咧，我想睇一睇個表十六嗰個計算嘅方法。嗱，表十六咧就明顯地咧，大部分都係一個學位不
係。
誒邊位可以答到啊？
改觀咧，其實呢樣嘢嚇。
個睇法即係話你你你話啊海外嘅學生真係冇乜用到本地資源呢個説法，你會唔會？
諗同世界好多地方都一樣，提供宿位係其中一個可以吸引到佢哋嚟香港嘅一個誒手手段嚟嘅。
啊，副秘書長，多謝主席。誒，我諗嗰個觀察誒，頭先啊，主席你代主席你嗰個觀察咧，都誒。
誒，究竟有即係我諗都係誒，在乎各大院校畀你哋嘅統計，就話有幾多同學啊申請縮位，同埋有幾多接納，畀幾多被拒絕，有冇呢一啲噉嘅啊大圍嘅誒統計數字咧？
所以，the figure there, two thousand and fifteen sixteen, shows eight thousand six hundred and sixty shortfall of bed spaces. That's when we take account undergraduates for one year, research postgraduates, overseas students and their entitlement. So that's the shortfall. If and of course it varies from year to year depending on the population. You asked us about, you asked me.
所以呢個係喺理論上，因為你係用緊權益計算，唔係話某個學生真係需要一個宿舍空間。係咪正確？嗯，需求超過供應，係當然嘅。特別係本地學生，需求超過供應。
明白嗱。頭先咧就誒，副秘書長喺上一節嘅問題嗰度問咧，就講緊呢啲誒非本地學生嗰誒超額收生嗰百分之二十，就話咧就冇乜用到本地嘅資源。但係咧，其實如果你睇翻呢個縮位呢一度咧，一。
因為你嗰個entitlement，即係話應該要有宿位提供嘅第一類咧，就已經係非本地學生啦。咁其實呢個説法嗱，土地更加係即係香港一個即係非常之珍貴嘅資源啦。噉你又有誒，我想問一問局方對呢個。
嗯。
需求 exceed 供應。
啊，多謝主席。
樣嘢嘅啫，或者兩樣都係啦嚇。阿局長或者邊位同事可以答到呢個問題咧？
no， you mean there's no no no such available statistics， is that correct， Doctor Alma？
都提到咧，我哋接納誒呢一個審計處呢個建議同埋呢一個觀察，我哋咧繼續要努力喺呢方面爭取嘅。阿Richard，would you like to say a bit more about the what's the progress last few years on the subject?
嘅基礎工程建設嘅一啲projection咧，會唔會做一個五年嘅計劃，或者十年計劃，然後先拎上嚟，即係逐樣逐樣同你傾咧，會唔會有啲噉嘅計劃嘅咧嚇？
students, but if it were if we were to do that, if we were to reduce the entitlement, there would be a strong worry that overseas students would would choose not to come and go elsewhere. But I'm confident that that in each each of our universities.
Well, I'm confident that demand exceeds supply because that's what the universities report. I don't have the numbers with me, but I'm sure I can find out. Can I supplement something Mr. Lowe said? One of the things we ask.
誒，即係話，究竟即係縮位，如果作為一種資源，即係當然，即係非本地學生係會需要用到呢一個資源嘅。咁而誒喺大學教育裏邊咧，其實即係我哋都要即係有幾個政策目標係需要達到嘅。當然就係話向本地學生提供即係足夠嘅。
教育機會啦，呢個係我諗最主要個目標啦。咁另外亦都有即係話係希望，即係話係可以提供到一個國際化嘅環境畀我哋個學生係作為一個學習嘅地方，亦亦都係另一個目標。所以即係話喺非本地生嗰個即係收取非本地生以一個超收嗰個形式係去收取咧，其實係用。
我哋係用緊呢一個方法去去達至一啲政策目標嘅。咁誒，無可避免地，即係頭先主誒代主席都有提及到，可能喺當中亦都會係有一啲資源嗰個考慮因素喺度。咁喺宿位上邊，的確係誒非本地學生，如果你要吸引佢哋嚟香港讀書嘅話咧，誒你即係我。
知道問題咧，就係點解即係你要諗一諗啦。雖雖然咧，即係呢一個恆工糧值嘅研究咧，並非即係針對嗰個政策。點解要定喺二十咧？如果一萬個即係二十就係三千人，噉你再計埋呢一啲嘅縮位，其實你要睇睇嗰個成本，同埋你話要吸引呢啲啊海外。
嘅誒同學嚟香港誒讀大學或者研究院嘅時候，究竟我哋嗰個誒成本同埋我哋個得益，究竟長遠嚟睇係咪即係成為一個正比咧？因為長期都係負數咧。咁咁呢個我諗係一個值得即係你哋誒無論。
喺個政策或者行工量就嚟講咧，都係值得研究嘅課題嚟嘅。嗱，講開嗰個縮位嘅問題咧，噉啊，頭先啊，Doctor阿ma就講咗話呢一個係一個in theory一個嘅計算。嗱，我想知道有冇一個統計數字，即係話二零一一一二至到一五一六呢啊五個年度咧？
Many of our universities take a survey called the International Student Barometer, which is asking students about about hostel places. And in in Hong Kong, we do we do about average for over for for countries across the world in terms of of providing accommodation for overseas.
啊，其實咧，而家你嗰個縮位不足嘅情況，其實係誒，嗱，我我想知道長遠嚟講，你哋有啲乜嘢嘅政策係去誒，即係解決呢個問題？究竟而家誒睇到嘅係一個資金不足嘅問題啊，抑或係一個即係土地問題咧？即係是打？
我頭先喺個主題嗰個簡介嗰陣時咧，我咧特別有強調呢一點嘅，因為理理論上同埋咧就即係最好能夠提供得到，咁但係咧就而家嗰個係啊嗰個基建嗰個配對基金嗰度咧，申請實際上嚟講競爭係好激烈嘅，因為好多其他嘅要求啊、醫療啊等等。
sorry啊。
冇咗，即係係不足。
And that's that's that's what we attempt to provide for the universities.
Yes, yes, chairman. Exactly that. There is a there is a formula which is aggregated to an entitlement.
第二年，比如科大啦，又過剩，咁呢個究竟係咪一個誒？
stable event, but of course, there's been an increasing population coming through the universities in those years with the four-year curriculum.
但係我哋呢度誒誒審計處長呢個報告度冇提到未來五年嘅一啲供應係咪冇？應該冇冇啲噉嘅資料係嘛？啊啊，審計處長。
In the main, prioritises them, and discusses them with EDB, and the projects go further up the chain, like normal capital projects for elsewhere in government.
只係一個閉門造居或者紙上談兵嘅in theory教空間，不，因為冇理由第即係一年間又少咗，第二年多咗，係咪？第日起咗間品樓出嚟，一年間會呢啲係咪又有一啲數字上嘅一啲嘅嘅嘅formula去去去計出嚟嘅咧？教空間嚇，唔該。
基金誒有咗之後咧，先可以規劃。但係大學自己亦都係可以有籌錢嘅誒，即係善款去捐助誒呢一方面去幫助下呢個誒成個建設嘅。咁兩方面我諗都係相輔相成嘅。好。
可能即係有有有啲有啲幾百尺嘅啊多咗，即係唔係叫叫多出嚟，係叫過剩之外咧？誒科大咧，二零一三一四年咧都都有一啲過剩。嗱呢個表話一二一三都係噉啊，但係呢個表好奇怪，點解會有一年間就會？
剩嘅對多好多，咁所以咧啊，我哋喺一個係嗰個資源啊，同埋呢個誒地上面嗰個資源咧，誒都係緊張。咁不過咧，我哋都你睇翻我哋呢幾年裏邊咧，我哋都盡力而為嘅，或者Richard可以再講一講咧，就咧我哋都有啲進展，但係就未如理想嘅。所以咧，我哋都繼續咧，我哋都。
多謝阿媽。No, I fully agree with the audit, and I fully agree with the the bureau. We simply have to press and convince the government that hostels and universities are a deserving cause. I know there are many competing issues, but also universities report that hostel life is an important.
我想問一問咧，即係嗰八大院校會唔會做一個啊？Capital project，尤其是呢一啲誒hostel嘅嘅嘅capital projection under。
如果佢要apply啊，去起一個即係宿舍嘅時候，可能個支出梗係多過三千萬嘅啦，一定會係under個C.W.F呢樣呢呢個category㗎啦。咁但係你冇理由無端端即係突然間話出年要起噉，但係佢都應該每間院校有冇做一個呢一啲？
Budget. Dottarmer. Pretty much, that's exactly how it works. Nearly all of them have got capital works master plans, which will of course include hostels. But and we do talk to them individually. We know what their their plans and programs are. UGC supports them and.
誒，多謝主席。我我哋冇嘅，但係喺誒頭先誒你提到嗰個誒最近遇到嘅問題咧，喺我哋三點八段咧，其實都有一啲表述，就係誒個學生嗰個申請縮位誒個成谷率啊，各方面都有啲誒有我。
just finish the beating of the。
所以，我 hope that answers the member's question.
President，啊，繼續啊，肯肯唔該，你繼續嚇。
我嘅誒誒教學面積呢樣嘢咧嚇，究竟邊幾個criteria用嚇？
Integrate, aggregate into a total entitlement. So we care about teaching space through classrooms.
埋都都都唔少嘅嗰啲嗰啲誒教學面積嗰個誒平方米計係係好多錢嘅。咁究竟你哋有啲乜嘢行動誒做咗或者做緊或者幾時會做完咧？啲reconciliation啊，Dr. Richard。
And space with each of the universities individually to make sure that each of our records are congruent as far as we can make it. It's quite a major exercise, but we realise that we have to make our records agree on a regular basis. So we do reconcile.
Library space, of course, teaching, research laboratories and offices, which are the main parts of universities. There are other parts of specialist accommodation which different universities have, clinical facilities in medical schools and the like. But those are those are also aggregated together.
我哋有啲發現嘅，咁同埋咧喺呢個誒三點一一段咧，亦都係描述咗誒目前呢個規劃嘅情況。噉就規劃嘅情況當然就要誒，即係申請呢個誒補助基金誒去誒非經常性嘅補助基金。
嗱，講咗嗰個縮位個誒不足嘅問題咧，表十七咧就講另外一樣不足嘅問題咧，就係啊教學空間。咁但係當當然咧唔會過剩啦。睇嘅全全個表入邊嗰五年都係即係各大院校啊，除咗啊領大嗰度。
But it's it's formula driven, different disciplines, different types of accommodation for different subjects. About the the case of UST, there must have been a building came online, which of course increases the floor space in a particular year. I'm sure it wasn't built in a year, but that that's that's the major semi-very
問一問咧，就都係誒十誒表十七嗰度咧。嗯，我我想知道究竟係用啲乜嘢嘅criteria去determine？你可以即係啊啊啊，Doctor阿明或者其他嘅同事可以講一講呢主要嘅criteria係邊幾類嘅criteria去計算呢一個？
Dr. Richard. Thank you. Thanks for the question. Well, it's largely formula-driven. We took a review of types of accommodation that are required in universities, and engaged a consultant a number of years ago to help us to find different types to aggregate into.
即係其實以即係計算呢個教學面積嘅需求咧，嗰個記錄係緊要嘅準確性同埋全面性。噉我睇翻表十八嗰度咧，咁誒幾間院校誒喺二零一六年六月做咗呢個即係一啲教學嘅誒面積嗰啲記錄啦。噉就有兩套記錄，一套係U。
鑄師自己嘅記錄一套就係啊大學本身自己嘅記錄，咁當然當中亦都有啲不同嘅演譯，令到係有啊唔同嘅。噉我亦都知道咧，呢一個所謂誒infantry咧，會係誒三年去去去去做一次嘅。咁誒就住呢一
啲不同嘅演譯或者數字上不同，你哋有冇一啲嘅啊行動去即係要求？誒一係就你睇下你自己recall，一係你就叫大學去recensure，一係就兩方面都坐低去recensure翻嗰個啊differences。因為其實呢度咧就即係加。
Richard。
嗯。
University space.
咧就係。
Dr. Richard。
好，嗱。
誒，或者再次確認翻咧，係咪咁多間大學都應該同樣用個同樣嘅方程式去計算咧？
好嘅，主席，我諗我暫時冇其他問題畀其他同事問。如果佢哋有問題嘅話，好，佢哋跟住嚇，係多謝主席，主席誒。
所以剛才就啊，多謝梁繼昌議員咧，開始咗呢個方向性嘅問題啦。噉我即就啲細節就再補充下少少啦。
公司之間，或者大學與大學之間，究竟係咪用同一個標準去report呢個academic space？呢個係我問題。嗯。
resource allocation issue, space allocation issue. Just that, depart from that, that's their business. But as far as reporting and discussion with UGC in terms of the total need, there is a common stand.
Yes, they do. They they they must for our purposes use our standards, our common standards in in discussing with us. If they have other internal.
好理解到香港嘅大家都人所共知嘅居住環境狹窄咧，包括我哋連住家嗰個空間咧非常之細咧。我哋喺計算呢個方程式嘅時候咧，我哋係有冇個本地嘅標準咧？定還是係參考外國嘅標準？定還是係點樣計出嚟嘅咧？
Thank you, Chairman. Yes, indeed, that's what we'll do. We'll do exactly reconciliation. The differences in the records. One of the reasons is the the times of measurement. They're not congruous in terms of and of timing, and that that explains some of the differences. But the way we do it is then to reconcile the actual usage of space.
係，即係你哋、你哋、你哋UGC同大學本身，即係可能冇一個共同嘅誒標的，即係standard，去話呢一個係一個誒教學嘅academic space啊？有有冇一個共同嘅嘅標準咧？嗱，教學教學嘅面積我知道真係真係講緊樓樓。
即係建築物入邊嘅嘅floor space應該係咁咪，我嘅解讀冇錯啊嘛。咁誒，比如一啲公共嘅空間等等，你哋有冇一啲嘅方法？即係比如話走廊，咁嗰啲又係咪dynamic space咧？咁嗰啲有冇？你有冇一套同一？我我所問嘅問題就係話，大學同UJ。
Richard, yes, thank you, Chairman. Yes, there is a common standard. Some of the differences arise because some universities have privately funded buildings or partially privately funded buildings, which we need to agree with them how much we're going to treat as in the public domain. And this is a this is never an easy
Discussion when we we want to count a lot of it, but the university wants to keep it private. So there's there's a lot of reconciliation, especially over over the private funding of some of the older universities in particular. But there is a common standard formula that we're all familiar with to to aggregate up the the needs of.
剛才咧就問及到有關於嗰個方程式咧，噉我睇翻第十住十一咧喺個三點一五段住十一嗰度咧個方程式咧就有其實有所謂嘅十種計算程式嘅，包括即係課室啊、研習空間啊、實驗室啊之類噉樣啊。我想理解下呢個誒方程式。
Richard。
yes.
not another standard imported from overseas.
Not just dorms, but part of the part of the the learning experience.
Programs that I wish were further ahead in terms of
管啊，室內體育設施啊，康樂設施啊，配套空間嗰啲就唔係即係嚴格嚟講就唔係教學空間嚟，咁嗰度又點計咧？
When we last reviewed this, it was and it was almost nine years ago, and I'm sure as far as hostels are concerned, let me just deal with that. That it will be the local standard.
Perhaps better described, learning space can include many many facilities, including hostels these days, where universities create what are called living learning communities, not just.
Rehabilitating some of the existing spaces that were perhaps built 30, 40, 50 years ago, but in the main, as a sector, I say we compare reasonably well with similar institutions across the world.
好，即係咁講咧，我哋應該都相對滿意咧，就係我哋嘅即係所謂academic spaces咧，就係國際水平嘅。雖然我哋嘅住宿嗰個空間咧，就係不符合國際水平，咁咁理解啱唔啱？
Living space, that's different. I understand, but as far as academic space goes, we benchmark across the world, and when we engage, we engaged an international consultant to help us do that in terms of the, you know, the space norms for our university.
Sure, I understand. I think, in broadly speaking, as a sector, we can we can match with most first-class research universities across the world. Now, there are individual differences amongst our universities. That I do I do understand, and there are some.
Academic space is different. Academic space is is common throughout the world. We surely would expect the facilities in our eight highly ranked Hong Kong universities to have the same level of facility and enjoyment as any other parts of the world leading universities, whether in Hong Kong or not. I take the member's point about about
好係當你劃劃分住誒宿舍同埋誒所謂academic spaces咧，誒嗰個所謂academic spaces即係嗰個學誒教學嗰個空間咧。嗰個其實因為你個方程式裏邊咧，就除咗宿舍嗰啲之外咧，剛才提及到嗰個方程式咧，住十筆嗰度咧係包咗好多啲即係圖書。
I think I disagree, sir. Learning is a 24/7 experience these days. Students are learning everywhere, even in the sports hall or whatever. And also, sports halls are usually converted into examination rooms for that particular time of the year. So it seems to me that academic space or
Richard。
好。
源嘅正確運用咧。
誒，第一咧就係你哋。
我哋當然 expect to be doing that in the foreseeable future.
多謝主席。
係啊，但係唔單止話係，即係我哋差唔多落後咗成十年咧，即係我必須指出咧就。
Well, how do we grasp that we are in line with practice across the world in using resources? The member is certainly right that we did the last methodology review.
希望咧進一步更加深入咁去國國際化啦嚇，咁呢兩個重點呢個方方向性嘅發展咧，似乎令到我哋以零零六年嘅統計咧，或者個估算咧，應該係大大失算嘅，或者落後於形勢。噉啊，理解啱唔啱，Richard？
係，剛才Doctor Armour咧，佢就講話，我哋已經有九年幾，其實應該十年咗啦。二零零六年就係對上一次嘅檢討啦，之後就冇再作檢討啦。咁期間當然都有我哋嘅新學制三加三加四嘅展開，亦都有我哋嘅所謂二零一零年嗰個報告咧，就教誒有一個教資會咧就誒。
Yo, thank you, Chairman. Again, yes, having another review certainly high in our priority list. As always, it's a question of priorities. When we went through the two thousand and five six methodology review and then the three three four curriculum, we wanted to wait until several other indicators.
Where available, like how the four-year undergraduate degree settled down, whether the new buildings that were built were fit for purpose during that period, and before we wanted to do, we didn't want to do a mid-stream review until the four-year curriculum had settled down. So we fully intend to do that. As I said, it's.
在
秘書處所誒保存嘅記錄咧，同埋學校理論上應該每誒大約三年度咧要提供嘅更新嘅數據咧，呢一方面咧就似乎嚇相對嚟講係非常不準確。你睇緊表十八，大家都知道咧，就嗰個差異都幾多嚇幾大嚇嘅呢個第一點咧。誒第二點咧。
就係話誒，你哋應該有根據你哋嘅辯覽咧，應該你哋可以委任外界機構去審核咧。但係又係十年到而家咧，零六年到而家咧都冇進行呢啲審核咧。咁而第三點咧，你哋又似乎一直都好似冇乜點樣去進行真正，除咗話個道原則上、道理上嚇。
誒誒theoretically個usage一個原則上點用之外咧，實際上點用咧，你哋完全係冇咧掌握，咁各方面都有落後，又唔準，又有差異。咁其實我哋點能夠即係話相信誒，譬如教資會個秘書處係有效地運載監管我哋誒資。
好。
Richard。
We are up to standard. Well, for the last three years.
One of those factors is is space.
gentlemen, they're not my figures. I think they're the audit commission's figures.
在《Times》高等教育補充，他們説，每美元GDP，香港是世界最高等級的行業。
所以，你 know， I I think I've explained where it's on our programme to do another methodological review in the near future.
係啊，即係但係會唔會有少少對唔住？講得比較直接啲咧，係咪一套講一套，做一套咧？實際嘅數字上，你哋而家咁完全落後於形勢，同落後於實際嘅情況咧，Richard。
但超過四小時嘅學生咧，本來應該有呢個機會申請縮位咧，都係有四十五個percent不成功。似乎呢啲數字，首先我想睇睇啲數字，誒，大家都認為準確嘅係咪？
And use of facilities, and it external benchmark, but it allows me to say reasonably confidently that we are benchmark in terms of facilities and space with peers across the world.
conciliation issue, and sure that's that's behind. But I'm still relatively confident that we're we're controlling it well. The 2005-6 review was a methodology about about space norms, not about an audit.
Methodology Review 2005-6， and that was considering whether the space norms were adequate. We do reconcile space and usage with universities regularly， so we are certainly ensuring that the state offices are managing their estate in terms of provision and use as regularly as possible. How do I know that？
If we're behind in terms of reconciling the record, yes, these are not straightforward because universities have complex estates, only some of which are publicly funded, and we have disputes about how much we can take from the private funded into the public domain, and there's a reconciliation.
或者我哋轉轉話題咧，睇翻剛才咧就誒阿梁繼昌如問過，不過可能佢就一下冇留意到三點八段咧，其實已經好詳細講咗嗰啲誒有關我哋縮位不足咧，就嗰個具體情況咧。咁特別三點八A咧就講非本地學生咧，就似乎咧就二十個percent。
不成功率嘅B咧就係本地研究生咧有成四十二個percent不成功率嘅，而C咧關於我哋學士即係有啲個理想就話最少有一年入住宿舍嘅經驗啦。咁其中咧就四十五percent係不成功嘅，而加埋誒C另外一個部誒部分咧就係話關於交通時間。
會錯。
誒。
Who's Richard?
誒嗱，或者咁講咧，你誒。
誒或者位置啊，定還是佢哋嗰個國際化有冇咩有冇咩correlation咩關聯性咧？
個影響咧，誒相比起，譬如話內地嘅非本地學生，同埋真係。
香誒中國嘅，或者亞洲以外嘅非本地學生咧，嗰個相對嘅影響性咧，係咪有好大嘅分別嘅？
Yes, thank you, Chairman. And I do understand the question. I don't have the data, but I'll I'll be happy to undertake to try and find out.
又或者誒，可唔可以局長又表達下意見咧？即係我哋而家被經常被批評話，我哋只係針對內地收生、內地嘅非本地學生啊。但係事實上喺收生困難上，宿舍或者缺乏宿舍呢個究竟有幾重要因素咧？
或者我講得清楚少少，就係話內地嘅非本地學生咧，可能佢哋就呢個縮位嘅不足嘅受影響因素咧，唔及於話嚟住，譬如嚟自美洲、歐洲、非洲嘅學生，佢哋對於縮位不足嗰個誒顧慮咧，可能會更加大咧。
剛才咧就有我哋啊委員咧就誒，我相信誒都強調過就係話，有關於香港嘅大學咧，普遍嚟講，雖然話想國際化，但係事實上咧只係大陸化，因為國外國嘅學生係非內地嘅學生咧個數字相當低嘅。我想理解下呢啲噉嘅縮位不足咧嗰。
Richard，啊，sorry，啊，Secretary。係啊，多謝主席。啊，都有影響嘅。我同大嘅接觸裏邊咧，特別係透過U.G.C，佢哋都話咧，最近呢幾年咧，學生嚟都話考慮到咧嗰個嗰個宿舍位數多少，所以都係有影響嘅。多謝主席。
好，咁呢個想或者再細緻睇睇咧，即係我哋睇到誒表十六嗰度咧，似乎領大咧就嗰個數字用講最近嗰一年咧，一五一六年咧係零嘅嚇，即係意思即係冇又冇不足又冇過剩啦。咁而咧就係誒相比起咧誒比較厲害嗰啲咧。
例如話誒成大咧誒二千零一一個咧，港大咧一八五八個咧，即係去到分別係三十六點五九percent同埋廿四點四九percent。呢啲係比較係誒高嘅誒不足嘅。咁想理解下誒，同佢哋本身嗰個所謂誒。
pass to。
睇啲嘢。
所以，我 sure 他們會 ensure 係適當、合適的。
Mr. Lam， that the site utilisation for construction of hostel.
unless the site determined otherwise, you know as you know some of the sites are very very cramped in some of our campuses.
Whether it's whether there's a there's an internationalisation issue in terms of demand and shortfall, again I refer to my earlier answer. I'll have to look into that in terms of the demand, Paul.
是，係，the the the site utilisation is not being built to the full plot ratio or exceed the plot ratio or the site utilisation are really restricted by UGC funding.
Highest priority. But yes, we underprovide. If we for for the the need that we want to give, we don't have the hostels available, and that's a deficit which we are still working to try and to try and close.
係啊，睇翻另外一間大學咧比較特別嘅，即係唯一一間大學係宿舍過剩啊。雖然係得三個數三呢個數字咧係較大，噉我哋係咪佢哋真係係咪佢收生不足嘅情況拉低咗佢，所以佢變咗佢就宿舍倒轉就多得滯咧？
誒，局長，啊，多多謝主席。交大有少少唔同嘅地方咧，因為咧教育嗰個專業咧嗰個要求度係唔同嘅，比較少啲係外國生，多數係本地生。特別呢個咧，根據呢個教育條例登記啊等等成咧，比較係本地嘅要求係有唔同地方都唔同嘅。
Thank you, chairman. Let me explain about Lingnan. First of all, it has a special privilege to what's called a stay small policy. It has 100% availability of theoretically 100% availability of hostel spaces, partly because of substantial private funding a number of years ago.
With the other universities, certainly some are more or less in deficit, partly due to their land situation, their history and background and the like. We certainly don't discriminate among universities in terms of approving their their programmes. The most needy is, is of course, Grant.
咁或者少少前瞻性咧，就住我哋而家你哋有意見話要過進一步深化嗰個所謂國際化啦。雖然咧，你哋咧就誒曾經喺即係包括三點一七段裏邊咧，就教主會秘書處咧就回應啊解釋啦，就係國際化其實好種形式嘅，就唔一定係多啲學生咁解，又包括咩國際策略。
啊！國際網絡啊，又話咩？國際多啲教職員啊，噉就即係等於都係國際化深化嘅噉。我想或者時間關係咧，問一問呢個問題，仲有一個就係話，究竟喺嗰個誒而家目前嘅環境之下，你哋咁缺乏宿舍情況之下，呢個噉嘅所謂國際化咧，是否係一個空中樓閣定係真正可行嘅咧？
局長係多謝主席。誒，呢個都係兩難嘅部分，但係咧，國際化我哋係必然要走嘅路，亦都對大學啊、對教育整個制度都係有誒好深遠嘅影響。所以咧，我哋喺做嘅過程裏邊咧，睇到譬如獎學金啊、其他嘅安排咧，有幾種情況出現嘅一。
就算佢唔係讀曬四年大學，可能係啲交換生，係啲短時嘅時間。第二都鼓勵咧，就即係佢哋用啲私人嘅捐獻啊，其他方面咧係去安排處理。第三咧，儘量喺一個誒宿舍裏邊咧繼續爭取有關嘅需要嘅地啊，同埋財政嘅資源幾個層面啲做。咁最後咧就呢個。
donations。
誒誒。
係啊！係
There have been cases like that.
我 ask 個 question for a specific reason.
The provision of more spaces for for students.
Well, that's unfortunate, and I'm happy to take that up with you outside. It's too late now. It's being built already. Okay.
of of hostels bases places by bureaucracy.
要一啲花四個鐘頭翻學嘅學生都冇宿舍住咧，呢個真正坎坷。
The university. Well, I hope those hurdles don't ever appear again, and I'll do my best to make sure bureaucracy never gets in the way with. It's not policies; it's just matter of.
但因為
係啊，國際化唔係淨係呢一個係啊學生或者係呢個誒宿舍嘅，亦都係咧就係呢個係國際嘅交流啊、研究啊、誒交換老師啊等等呢方面啲教授啊，都係其中另外一種嘅做法嚟嘅。多謝主持人。係。好。啊，我哋問到呢個先啦，主席。Okay，誒，If I may ask Richard before，before
Thank you for the question. Certainly not by UGC funding, because that that would be that that's a public works issue whether the grant is given to the to the university to build the hostels. I assume that we when projects come forward for hostels or academic buildings, we're advised by the government subject.
that the site they can build more hostel, but you but UGC have not given the approval to build more hostel because of your of your your funding requirement. The other funding they they could have top up the building of hostels by
policy as such, because you can have built, say for instance, use an example of 500, you can only allow them to build 300 because of your your requirement that that is only for. It's nothing to do with plot ratio. Okay, you understand what I'm saying? I think I understand. You are actually deterring the provision of of
But but I hope that you can review your policy on this, make them more flexible because such a shortage of hostel places that every possible means that they have not violated the law and utilising the the the construction cost to build more is.
No harm to to UGC. It's only benefit to the student population. I I couldn't agree more, sir. Taking taking, I have reason to ask this because I've witnessed a situation like this in one of the university, not the present university that I'm a council of, but in.
主席啊，誒之前咧有個私人發展商咧賣個超細嘅樓盤嘅時候咧，就攞大學宿舍咧做個比喻，就見到嗰呢啲大學宿舍咧，覺得好感動，就未聽過有家長投訴啲學生宿舍咧就好坎坷。噉啊，現在咧誒。
省委主張。
係內地生嚟嘅，即係有一萬宗。
但係，居然都係有四十五個percent係唔成功嘅。
啊，對唔住我，即係啱問開。明白，明白。
嘅係啊，修業期內住宿舍一年嘅申請嘅啫。
條數應該係咁計啊，係咪咪嗱？佢佔咗一萬宗嘅申請。
非本地學生佢誒獲分配縮位嘅，佢係一萬七千九百一十五宗申請。
你話噉樣係咪佔咗本地大學嘅資源咧？我就睇唔到點解係佔唔到咯。即係我睇阿阿沈毅處長個理解係咪噉啊？
3.8 fig the figures in 3.8 those are the directive orders figures. So I just like to clarify the figures whose figures are this.
我真係諗唔到咧，喺香港咧，喺邊啲地方要翻學要花兩個鐘頭，放學要花兩個鐘頭噉嘅情況，居然有四十五個percent嘅申請係唔成功嘅。
頭先啊，教育局不斷強調內地或者非本地嘅學生對香港呢個大學嘅資源其實冇影響嘅處處慮。嗱，我哋睇翻三點八A嗰段啦。
誒誒數字嚟嘅，嚇審計署又話係政府嘅數字喎。咁咧，我哋想想佢係邊個數字？誒，Richard，you know you when when the honourable project asked you a question，you said those figures in three point。
有三千六百一十一宗係誒唔成功嘅，嗯，有兩成係唔成功嘅。O.K.我計一計條數，即係成功嘅大概有萬四宗啦。萬四宗係非本地學生嘅申請嚟嘅，嗯，噉啊，非本地學生當中咧，大概七成幾咧？
誒，我哋呢度啊，嗰啲資料咧係由呢個誒秘書處嗰度誒抽取出出嚟嘅，但係冇一個細分就係唔知道係內地嗰橛係幾多啊？嗯嗯。O.K.嗱，阿主席，我哋睇埋C嗰度啊，C一一萬八千一百九十九宗申請嘅。
即係大家睇到，我唔係話要完全排佢內地嘅學生或者非本地嘅學生，但係你係擺咗咁多資源畀一啲非本地學生，令到本地生咧每日花四個鐘頭來回車嘅，都仲有差唔多一半人係冇宿舍。呢個係非常非常之。
啲荒謬對本地生不公平嘅政策嚟㗎嘛？即係我，我唔知道教育局有咩解釋啊！啊，教育局長啊，或者我先講講啱啱傾開頭先啊，破問嗰個三點八嗰啲資料咧，啱你講出嚟咧啊，秘書長咧就就話咧，依啲係誒審計處嘅。
二嗰段咧就話係四個鐘頭。
誒係第三點二九段啊！
或者我請誒助理助理處長解釋一下我哋啲數據。唔該曬你。
噉我我唔知道可唔可以稍後叫佢提供個數字啊？噉啊，我我最後問埋一個問題咧，就係。
話嗰筆賬緊要啦，就誒over十五到十八年嘅預期嘅係有兩成二，呢個係誒已完成主要基本工程項目嘅，跟住表二十咧就已完成改建加建同埋維修嘅。
就呢度係咁講嘅，審計署咧就預期嘅情預期情況嘅帳齡啊，分析進一步顯示咧就誒有二十九個決算帳目啊，佔八十一個percent嘅預期超過三年，表十九咧。
係多謝主席。誒，我哋嗰啲數字咧就係喺誒誒秘書處嗰度攞翻嚟嘅。噉，但係咧就誒，我哋喺個審計報告嗰啲數字咧係我哋整理過嘅，即係我哋誒每間大學嘅數字噉，然之後一個做咗一個分析，就綜合咗審計報告嗰啲數字出嚟嘅。嗰啲數字就係我哋做出嚟。
但係，個原始資料咧就係喺誒秘書處嗰度攞翻嚟嘅。即係兩個都對嘅。啊啊，Richard，let's comment on this before you answers.誒誒，before the answers to about the travelling time. Yeah. Can you answer this question on the figures? Do you verify the figures given? Make the
Number tabulated by the director of audits are correct because the source of information comes from your secretariat. Well, then I'm I'm happy to trust the director of audit always. But if if it came from the secretariat, then we must have asked the universities. Whether universities are providing valid and reliable.
Data, I hope they are, but it's a complicated question. But the university do provide all the details of their hostels to you. Yes, they do. I do that because I sit on one of the university's development committee, which they do supply all details information to you. So those are quite accurate. Sure, I'm confident the figures are not.
misrepresentative。Okay，that's good。I just want to clarify this。啊，局長，你可以答翻啊。啊，議員噉。係啊，主席，我申請副秘書長答答。副秘書長啊。多謝主席。咁頭先，林議員個問題其實喺較早前啱啱啱啊，梁議員亦都有提及過，其實係相類似嘅問題。咁誒，我亦都解釋咗，即係話誒，我。
我哋政策目標都係有幾個唔同嘅政策目標，包括係就本地學生嗰個誒提供嗰個一定數量嘅學額，而另外就係喺國際化嘅目標嗰度，我哋都係要係吸引一啲誒非本地嘅學生嚟香港讀書，而係提供宿舍亦都係其中一個可以吸引佢哋嚟嘅地方。咁喺呢一方面，我哋係亦都誒。
一定必須承認係會係有一啲政府嘅公共資源係會花咗落去嘅。咁呢個我頭先亦都喺誒解釋嗰個情況，同埋回答一兩議員嗰個問題都係有又有提到。咁另一方面咧就係話誒，我哋教育局同埋教資會咧，亦都係會繼續即係就，因為我哋都察覺即係縮位不足係一個問題嚟嘅。噉我。
幾一年？
呃，Richard。
要要核帳啊？定係唔使核㗎？呢啲帳？
超過十年到十五年咧，仲有兩個噉啊！
或some of those that gone out of business. I think we need to more information to satisfy our
some of those are partly partly contribute, so you have to really can you give us more details?
The stuff of your control is between contractor parties between the university and the contractors. Is that? It's a combination. Do not do not
There are others where the university is still in dispute with the with the contractor, still negotiating various various different claims. So there are a number of a number of particular reasons.
thirst for for information. No, no problem. Just to go back to your earlier question. I'm certainly not trying to say UGC has no responsibility. We do, and I do personally to put pressure on the university to settle the accounts. 哎，主席，我諗。
We have to work with the universities to try and get these wrapped up. No questions. Not that we haven't been. It is difficult, and we'll certainly redouble our efforts to to try and get these wrapped up as soon as we can. In other words, that.
我哋係就呢一方面咧，我哋會係繼續即係喺我哋嗰個公務工程裏邊係會繼續係爭取即係資源，係去起興建呢個宿舍。噉我哋係過去呢三個年度，我哋係即係成功係可以爭取到有兩個項目係落實到。咁喺未來咧，我哋都希望可以繼續爭取到誒相應嘅資源嚇。阿主席啊！
即係多謝政府咧，終於承認咧，其實誒內地生或者非本地生咧，對香港嗰個大學嘅資源係佔用咗相當。噉我我想誒睇下政府或者係審計處，唔知有冇一個數字咧？如果冇嘅，稍後可唔可以提供咧？嗱，而家睇翻誒三點八C誒。
誒交通來回嘅學生咧，就四廿五個percent係唔成功啦。如果去到三個鐘頭咧，其實嗰個數字會唔會上到去七成、八成，甚至更加高嘅？因為其實我覺得咧，四個鐘頭嘅交通來回係極不合理嘅。其實三個鐘頭咧，已經係好長程嘅路途啊！喺香港嚟講，噉。
即係超過七年到十年咧，就八個。即係即係，我覺得呢啲噉嘅糊塗帳咧，即係十幾年都唔走去跟翻，我唔知道應該邊個去負責咯。其實定係呢啲公家錢唔係好需要去核數，唔需要理啲帳目嘅咧。阿阿梁繼昌議員其實一般應該要。
On the final accounts, some have straddled over 18 years, and some some within two to 18 years. Can you explain why this is the case? There are various reasons. A number of them, for example, the contractor went out of business more than 10 years ago, so it's difficult to reconcile accounts with a with a non-existing corporation.
Could not been able to do the final accounting for the project. Is that so? It's a combination of parties. Certainly, but there are different projects. Some of those projects are actually funded, controlled by UGC. Yeah. Well, through have you? Is there some of this project? And some are doing.
的確。
Richard。
澄清咗個定義未咧？誒，Richard。
嗯，係咪啊？啊，係，多謝主席。嗯。
啊，那係Beyond me，我唔知，但係收佢哋利息，如果如果係，唔係，唔係，係咪實行嘅？
幾時開始試誒誒揾呢一個澄清嘅？
Those cases that the return sum, whether included interest or not, is a simple question as that.
Right, we we we began as soon as we saw the the audit report. We started talking to the bureau. I'd like to go back a moment.
啲錢咧要還翻畀政府，呢一樣嘢係非常之重要。噉我簡單啲想問咧，就係咧，誒，如果延遲咗還咧，即係譬如話你哋真係揾到個三年啦，噉啊真係延遲咗還，你又覺得佢冇理由嘅，咁嗰啲計唔計息嘅咧？如果還錢嘅時候？
On this table, so that at least we have some answers. Because rather than slamming you on a on on a general conclusion, because we have to write that report that such a long time is impossible. So you have to give the reason. How many of those eighteen years under arbitration or medi?
秘書處嗰邊咧要回應，究竟呢啲噉嘅誒預期嘅情況嘅原因係乜嘢嘢，同埋佢過去十幾年嚟對呢啲預期情況作出過啲乜嘢嘅跟進行動，有冇同相關嘅機構作相關？
嘅回報，即係如果唔係，好似畀人覺得淨係審計署查咗出嚟，你哋先至即係揭露啲噉嘅情況出嚟，係咪咁咧？定係你一路係跟進住咧？我諗誒，今日未必需要好仔細逐項去講。係啊，我諗你畀個補充嘅資料我哋啊。唔該，主席係有冇其？
其他問題冇啦，唔該。冇咧，就係餐飲，你跟住嚇啱曬，主席，我都係諗住問呢個部分嘅。噉啊，首先咧，當然咧，由幾時開始計數呢個都係一個謎嚟㗎。噉啊，因為咧兩種項目即係超過三千萬同埋誒唔夠三千萬咧，誒嗰個嗰個解釋有少少唔同㗎喎。噉啊誒超過三千萬嗰個。
咧就係用呢一個誒設施啓用開始計數嘅咁咧就誒誒少過三千萬咧就話實體工程完成咧就開始計嘅噉啊誒大額嗰個咧就計三年啦，細額嗰個就計三個月嘅。其實三個月都相當緊啊，講真嗰句噉，但係唔緊要，既然規例係寫咗啦，好噉我就就問，但係其實生。
三點二五段咧，誒呢一個報告都寫得好清楚咧，就係誒秘書處就覆咧，就話兩者個定義係相同嘅。咁咧就誒仲話咧，即係二零零七年二月修訂個變冷嘅時候咧，就已經係採取呢一個誒同一樣嘅，即係用翻呢個結算工程誒個定義，就以結算工程。
誒決算帳目，即係用翻誒嗰個統一嗰個解釋啦，就係用呢一個叫做實際完成嘅咁噉。但係我就想問下咧，誒但係誒你都會話咧，就係話再去問呢一個誒誒呢一個財經事務及副務局澄清嘅。我想問下。
而且。
Going forward, when we start the clock ticking.
The return of money to the government.
收錢，但係我想問一問咧，咁決定係佢係咪真係？
哦，是是， certainly a practice that we don't apply a an interest penalty. No, no, it's not interest. Is who decides.
即係點講咧？即係唔還錢啊！過咗期唔還呢一個決定係咪UGC做嘅先？應該係，但係呢個睇佢答到冇。好，阿Richard。
Well, we did have a clear definition, and it's it's it's we thought we were right, but it seems that we we need to be advised by more specialist departments, which is why we're we're working out when we.
We take UGC takes it in cooperation with some of the other relevant bureau and departments who are technical advisers and like architectural services and the like. Can you also highlight how many of these cases had in the past during the study period?
Sure. And the relevant departments. Yes. What are the relevant department? Happy to do. Thank you. Thank you.咁好啦，我亦都誒想問下啦，就誒誒，噉你哋點即係如果係啲咁曖昧都未有定義嘅情況之下，其實你點樣決定究竟佢係咪過咗期咧？
Okay, as far as I'm aware, no.係佢唔知道有層誒，佢誒唔知道有interest啊？定係過往係其實冇冇呢啲噉樣嘅個案出現過？有冇呢啲個案出現過？就係佢哋斷定係遲還咗嘅。係係，誒，你understand the question？
There's no question at all that the UGC didn't start worrying about the capital projects simply because the audit highlighted it. We've been working on it constantly. It's a priority. We review it at our regular committee. The outstanding projects that the officers follow up. Can we do better? Yes, and we must do better for sure.
and that that that makes it partly UGC's responsibility to make sure the universities deliver on time。啊，主席，我哋都我我我哋好公道嘅，我哋我哋逐樣逐樣嚟啦。我哋先問咗個我先問咗嗰個誒解釋咧，或者個定義咧，因為個定義就係斷定咗嗰個時限嘅開始性，而係幾時咧要將剩翻個。
Of of when do we start the clock ticking? When when the when situation, just as highlighted by Tanya, the honourable chair, that if the fund that they have hold back money, which is should have be returned, right, to UGC, yes, there must have been cases in.
yes，as as far as I'm aware, we take advice from financial services and treasury bureau because the money doesn't come back to UGC, it comes back to the treasury. UGC has no, there's only a mailbox. 好，噉啊，我哋寫封信去問下啊，發啊呢個啊treasury department啊陳家強哋咧，因為佢哋負責啲。
We can't reset the clock going backwards。咁噉，主席，我又想問下啦。咁咧，因為喺第三點二六，對住係誒誒審計處有有有SFTB係啊，又唔記得咗你喺度添。係誒，多謝主席。誒，關於定義嘅問題咧，就誒秘書處誒大學資助委員會秘。
司署嗰邊咧已經根據咗誒審計處處長嘅意見啦，就徵詢咗我哋關於設施啟用嗰個定義嘅。噉我哋亦都響誒十二月誒六號嗰日咧，就畀咗我哋誒嗰個睇法啊，對方知道。咁基本上咧，我哋覺得所謂嘅設施啟用咧，應該係指嗰個有。
關項目佢係誒投入呢個功能運作就為之誒設施啟用啦。咁因為咧有啲誒項目咧你完成咗之後咧，仲要一啲測試期啦嚇。噉啊，當你誒過咗呢測試期個功能運作係暢順開始嘅時候咧，噉就應該係定義為呢個設施啟用啦。咁應該咧就唔包呢個。
所謂嘅缺漏維誒修補期嘅，因為呢個缺漏修補期咧，其實可長可短嘅冇錯。咁同埋咧，就即係誒，你少修少補咧，亦都唔會影響佢功能運作。噉，所以我哋嘅睇法咧，其實係即係一個即係誒比較common sense嘅睇法啦。好啊，唔該曬，因為啊，主席啊，你如果睇埋三點二六段咧，嗰個嗰個就更加。
令到嗰個開始計算佢究竟係有錢定係冇錢，就更加撲朔迷離啦。因為咧呢一個缺漏修補期咧，就可能係一年啊，或者更長嘅時候噉，所以咧我就即係想知道究竟誒佢哋有冇話，例如係計算埋呢一個咧？因為如果誒似乎咧就。
Right, I'll have to. I'll have to.
嘅畀我哋，咁第二部分啊，局長可能答一答啦。
出去，佢哋走去問佢有冇同意過你，畀你去問，亦或者你嘅睇法同唔同意佢咁？
Take a look at the Treasury Bureau's advice, which hasn't reached me yet. So I'll have to read that, and they give it to you on December the sixth. Yes, today is December the twelfth. Yes.
質啦嚇，噉係有意無意啊？定係嗰個誒情節係點樣樣咧？咁然之後先作一個決定嘅。咁誒，我哋係會確保咧，係即係誒公堂嗰邊咧係得到保障啦。好多謝你。但係以往係點做咧？
咁喺呢次嘅事件之後，你哋會會唔會即係譬如話誒按年先需要佢誒彙報一下有冇啲個案係已經拖咗好耐而後未處理？因為咧，我點解見到噉樣咧？因為你睇下誒呢個政府的回應三點三四段C咧，哇喺～
副副副將打答係，多謝主席。主席係，多謝主席，亦都多謝阿陳議員嘅問題。噉就呢啲誒工程項目嗰邊嗰個誒監管同埋，即係有關於佢啲項目審計嗰個結果咧，基本上我哋係交由翻比較資會去全權負責嘅。
佢哋都會考慮埋呢一點嘅喎，係咪咧？咁即係如果考慮埋呢一點，我想問翻啊UGC嗰邊誒教資會係咪即係話，如果嗰個缺漏修補期你哋係計埋嘅話，係咪即係話誒一日仲係修補當中嘅話咧，都唔當呢個係設施已經係啟用咗，即係唔當係設施啟用㗎？Richard
好快有啲就已經追翻咯，即係呢個帳目，咁似乎即係檢視可能係有用嘅，即係除咗審計署之外咧，當然好有用啦。咁但係會唔會局肯即係誒去研究一下，唔好加加佢哋太多嘅工作，可能每一年啊等等，會唔會一個適合嘅時期去定期檢查一下咧？局長。
我唔 sure，它喺我辦公室，但係唔喺我身邊。O K，啊，啊，劉生，你可唔可以講你哋有冇計息嗰度啊？即係你都喺度，即係遲咗，即係應該要交翻畀畀政府，政府。多謝主席，我諗即係誒，係咪需要誒計及利息呢個問題咧？就應該要視乎個別嘅個案嘅，咁要睇下嗰個性。
誒，以往可能要睇翻嗰個實際嘅例子，我哋當時考慮嘅原因。呢啲實際例子，我哋睇。我哋誒秘書處嗰邊將來會做，但係以往做過乜嘢，我要睇一睇，好冇？我哋睇翻以往嘅例子，誒，畀誒委員會嗰邊考慮。唔該，誒主席好。噉我都亦都想了解下咧，即係譬如話。
誒，我我我我明白咧。U.G.C佢都話佢哋會再盡量做得好啲，或者係係係有方法可以再改善嘅。噉，但係我都想瞭解一下咧，就住有啲個案咧，真係真係超標㗎嘛？即係例如有啲十八年啊，即係超過三千萬嗰啲，咁跟住少過三千萬嗰啲咧，都有去到十五年。咁其實當中係點樣跟？
進啦，誒，佢哋做咗啲乜嘢，或者你哋會幾密去誒去復檢一次啦？咁誒，另外我都想問下，其實教育佢哋點樣同教育局嗰邊瞭解，而教育局都有冇去審視翻呢啲嘅個案嘅？即係誒，頭先你第一部分咧，阿林議員都叫佢畀一張誒，畀一畀張誒，佢哋解。
係。
Okay. Thank you.
嗯。
我哋問埋呢頭，我哋完咗佢今日好嘛？
阿阿朱姐，我哋可唔可以都睇一？我哋會唔會有機會有一個誒，即係副本睇一睇個解釋㗎？
唔該曬，thank you，Richard。唔該曬，審計處長啊，阿劉生，我唔記得咗你喺度添。你劉生，你F.S.T.V.你第一次嚟啊？歡迎嚇，對唔住，冇記得歡迎你添。
我哋會唔會有機會可以都問財經及誒財經事務及服務局？我哋會問佢攞嘅。好，啊，主席，我仲有一條好簡單跟進嘅啫。明白。誒，主要都係就翻三點二。
主席，我未見到嗰個文件啦。頭先啊Richard都答咗咧，就咧佢都翻去再詳細啲睇。但係頭先咧，我喺主體嘅回應我都提咗嘅啦，就係咧有關呢啲各項嘅一啲跟進同埋一啲嘅討論咧，我哋都希望咧UCC睇曬之後咧，我哋坐低長期叫做我都要跟進一下㗎。
做個答覆佢答覆啦，咁未做個答覆嗰陣時，你知唔知依件事？你理解幾多？你同唔同意？因為你都要保保護住依個UGC嘅，你同唔同佢哋有冇你同意？有冇同你諮詢過？因為依牽涉到錢銀嘅問題喺度。
採用咗同一個定義啦，噉樣噉我就想了解下，其實幾時發現？同埋如果既然仲有呢啲噉樣嘅分別，即係又有攞到意見啊，你哋幾時會採取誒措施，會盡快修正你哋嗰個誒辯攬啊，同埋相關嘅一啲字眼咧？唔該，主席。
多謝主席，亦都多謝啊陳議員嗰個提議。咁有翻有關於點樣樣去改善，即係話以後有關於呢啲噉嘅工程項目嗰個監管或者跟進嘅話咧，誒，我哋教育局會同教資會去商討，睇會唔會有一個方法，或者係喺呢一方面可以做得更好，而亦都可以達至話唔會係加強，即係加重咗佢哋嗰個工作量。因為點解？
但係咧，你下次嚟攞錢嘅，即係嚟立法會攞錢咧，大家都會問嘅，噉就希望對你以後工作都可能方便啲啊。生日機會係錢使使少咗係好少有，從來我哋咁耐都好少有噉嘅情況。但係話者教資局可以有呢啲噉嘅情況，第二我想問一問。
啦，即係呢個機會，阿局長，你哋同唔同意Treasury嗰邊解釋呢個commissioning of facility嗰個點解係要問你哋要問啊Treasury咧？你哋有冇嗰個情？你哋參與喺呢度，你都係你管佢哋㗎嘛嚇？噉你有冇睇到個情情況係點會咁？
喺依個誒三點三三三點三三嗰度咧，佢就係即係英文嗰嗰段啊。Seek clarification from the Secretary of Financial Services and Treasury on the definition of commissioning of the facilities。噉我哋問下你個局喺依一度做咗乜嘢？一佢又有十二月六號畀。
呢個出台完嘅。O K，好好，主席，我主要都係問翻咧嗱，因為誒誒，其實你哋幾時，即係我想問下U G C，其實幾時咧發現咧，即係就住呢個設施啟用同埋實體工程完成呢個定義係有出入，因為咧你見見到佢個答覆就係自二零誒二零零七年嘅二月修訂咗變案之後就已經。
個睇法。
嗯，Well， if we need to revise the definition or further explain it, then we'll do so as soon as we practically can in our overall review of the the director of audit's recommendations。幾時發現有嗰個落差？We have a timetable for that。唔係唔係，主席，幾時發現呢兩個字眼嘅？唔有有兩組字眼。佢而家啱啊！佢未睇封信，佢六號十月。
月六號咧，佢先係咪十二月六號啊？十二月六號先寫封信去，仲未喺去喺去。我下次再補問。下次下次補問好冇？好嚇，好多謝各位。我哋今次完咗依部分，我哋再會約大家時間去跟進另外啲部分喺依個第二章誒六十七號報告嗰度。好多謝。